Preliminary Guide to the James Southgate Papers, 1794-1944 and undated, bulk 1851-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Southgate papers 1794-1944 and undated, bulk 1851-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southgate, James Haywood, 1859-1916.
2.4 linear feet Extent: 1926 Items
Educator, insurance agent, and civic leader, of Durham, N.C. Family, business, and personal correspondence (chiefly after 1851) of Southgate and of his family. The material concerns Southgate’s insurance business, life in North Carolina, the establishment of Durham, N.C., and of Duke University; the Southgate family in the Civil War, Reconstruction in North Carolina, education and civil activities in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Virginia, and schools in Durham; and the activities and genealogy of the Southgate family. Correspondents and persons mentioned include Mattie Logan Southgate Jones, Delia Haywood Wynne Southgate, James Haywood Southgate, and Myra Ann Muse Southgate.
RL.01237
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rubenstein Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Southgate Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer and gift in 1944-1959.
Biographical Note
Educator, insurance agent, and civic leader, of Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
Family, business, and personal correspondence (chiefly after 1851) of Southgate and of his family. The material concerns Southgate’s insurance business, life in North Carolina, the establishment of Durham, N.C., and of Duke University; the Southgate family in the Civil War, Reconstruction in North Carolina, education and civil activities in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Virginia, and schools in Durham; and the activities and genealogy of the Southgate family. Correspondents and persons mentioned include Mattie Logan Southgate Jones, Delia Haywood Wynne Southgate, and Myra Ann Muse Southgate.
Subject Headings
Jones, Mattie Logan Southgate; Southgate, Delia Haywood Wynne; Southgate, James Haywood, 1859-1916; Southgate, Myra Ann Muse; Southgate family; Duke University -- History; Education -- Southern States; Insurance -- North Carolina; Public schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- North Carolina; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Women -- North Carolina -- Social conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- History; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; North Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; North Carolina -- Social life and customs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- Southgate Correspondence, 1794-1934, (4 boxes)
  - 1794-1852 (Box 1)
  - 1853-1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1881 (Box 1)
  - 1882-1883 (Box 1)
  - 1884-1889, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1890-1895 (Box 2)
  - 1896-1899 (Box 2)
  - 1900-1904 (Box 2)
  - 1905-1907 (Box 2)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 2)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 3)
  - 1914 Jan.-1914 Oct. (Box 3)
  - 1914 Nov.-1915 (Box 3)
  - 1916 (Box 3)
  - 1917-1919 (Box 3)
  - 1920-1925 (Box 3)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 3)
  - 1928-1930 (Box 3)
  - 1931-1934 (Box 3)
  - Undated and envelopes, (3 folders) (Box 4)
- Southgate-related Correspondence, 1839-1860, (1 folder)
  - Pleasant Trice letters, 1852-1860 (Box 4)
  - Harry S. Baker letters, 1863 (Box 4)
  - D.W. Jordan letters, 1854 (Box 4)
  - Sarah Tillinghass letters, 1849, 1853 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1839-1860 (Box 4)
  - Envelopes (Box 4)
- Writings, Organizations, and Subjects Files, 1891-1932 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - About Duke University/Trinity College, undated (Box 4)
  - On Women's Work, undated (Box 4)
  - Writings, 1913-1932 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Records of the Durham Athletics (M-2081), 1891 (Box 5)
  - Durham Civic Association Notebooks (M-2074), 1915-1918, (2 volumes) (Box 5)
- Geneology, 1918-1924 and undated, (5 folders)
  - 1918-1924 and undated (Box 5)
- Financial Papers, 1900-1929, (2 folders)
  - 1st National Bank account book, 1900 (Box 6)
  - Bills and receipts, 1920-1929 (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Printed Material, 1900-1944, (3 folders)
  - 1900-1944, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Photographs, 1938 and undated, (1 folder)
  - 1938 and undated, (1 folder) (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous, Undated, (2 folders)
  - Recipes (Box 6)
  - Order of parade (Box 6)
  - Notebook of pressed flowers (Box 6)
  - Curriculum vitae in the form of business cards of Geo. M. Moulton (Box 6)